Continuing our time with conditions, I will
introduce a potential problem with our score
and level code. I have the same code in this
file, 213-else, from the previous file. I will
change the score to 3000 and run the code. What
displayed? Nothing. That might be the logic you
want in an app like this, but you will likely
want a message to display if a player has yet
to reach a level so that the player at least
knows what is going on within a game and we
avoid overall confusion within the app. The else
keyword allows one to perform an action that runs
as part of a condition when the if condition is
not true and none of the other elif conditions
are true. Listen to a real-life application of
else. If it is sunny and over 80 degrees outside,
I will go to the beach. Else, if it’s sunny, I
will play golf. Else, I will stay at home. The
stay at home part applies if it’s not sunny at
all. For our code example, we want to let the
game player know that if a target score has
not been exceeded, the player needs to work
to reach a level. Thus, starting on line 7, I
will add the else keyword with a colon. Then,
on the following line, I will indent four spaces
to match these indents and add this statement:
print(“You need to score higher to reach a
level”). Then, I will skip a line and add a
print statement that is not indented, thanking
them for playing. Recall that statements not
indented are not part of a condition and, thus,
should always run. Before running this code,
know this about indents: Python recommends four
spaces for an indent, which many apps will give
you when using the Tab key on the keyboard.
You can use the Tab key or add spaces manually,
but for the code to work correctly, you need
to be consistent in your indentation methods.
I always use four spaces, but the indentation
method is your choice. Just be consistent with
your indentations. I will rerun this code now,
and we see the two messages we anticipated: that
the player needs to get to a higher score, and the
player was thanked for playing. I will test this
code again, using scores over 5000 and over 10000,
and, in each case, we see the results we want:
that the player has reached a level matching the
score and that the player is thanked for playing.